Speck-Choate Photograph Collection 1879-1881 Mss.B.Sp3c
American Philosophical Society
Speck-Choate Photograph Collection
1879-1881
Mss.B.Sp3c
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet 27 photographs
The United States Indian School at Carlisle, Pa., was founded by Gen. Richard Henry Pratt in 1879, and served as a model for government boarding schools for Indians until its closure in 1918. Over 10,000 students enrolled at the Carlisle Training School during its 39 years, where, separated from their native cultures, the students were prepared for work in industrial and manual labor and socialized into "civilized" life. Given new white names to replace their Indian ones, the students were prohibited from speaking their native languages, were instructed in Christianity, and were fed, clothed, and housed under strict military discipline. The 27 photographs in the Speck-Choate Photograph Collection were taken by J. N. Choate, a local commercial photographer in Carlisle, Pa., and collected by the anthropologist Frank G. Speck. Choate advertised "Photographs of all the Indian Chiefs that have visited the Indian Training School at Carlisle Barracks, also of children in native and school costumes" and were intended to document the benefits of civilization that the school brought to Indians. Typical images include "before and after" shots of students in native dress and school uniforms, the school band, and shots of the students at work in the saddle shop and making shoes. Choate also took a number of images of visiting chiefs in traditional dress, including the Lakota chief Spotted Tail, and the Cheyennes Man on Cloud and Mad Wolf. One photograph depicts Richard Henry Pratt seated with Quaker supporters. Among the tribes represented are the Lakota, Laguna, Cheyenne, Creek, Lipan, and Pueblo.
Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902
Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
Bibliography
Adams, David Wallace, Education for Extinction: American Indians and the Boarding School Experience, 1875-1928 (Lawrence: Univ. of Kansas Press, 1995).
Related Archival Materials note
The Charles James Rhoads Papers (Mss.B.R34) contain a number of letters to and from Richard H. Pratt, founder of the Carlisle School.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Bequest of William Francis Gray Swann, 1962.
Scope and Contents note
The 27 photographs in the Speck-Choate Photograph Collection were taken by J. N. Choate, a local commercial photographer in Carlisle, Pa., and collected by the anthropologist Frank G. Speck. Choate advertised "Photographs of all the Indian Chiefs that have visited the Indian Training School at Carlisle Barracks, also of children in native and school costumes" and were intended to document the benefits of civilization that the school brought to Indians. Typical images include "before and after" shots of students in native dress and school uniforms, the school band, and shots of the students at work in the saddle shop and making shoes. Choate also took a number of images of visiting chiefs in traditional dress, including the Lakota chief Spotted Tail, and the Cheyennes Man on Cloud and Mad Wolf. One photograph depicts Richard Henry Pratt seated with Quaker supporters. Among the tribes represented are the Lakota, Laguna, Cheyenne, Creek, Lipan, and Pueblo.
Choate's photographs are mounted on standard stock, include 19 cabinet cards and 8 boudoir cards. Although some of the photographs are titled by hand and signed by Choate, most have printed backmarks with a few including lists of other available images and advertising pitches.
Biographical/Historical note
The United States Indian School at Carlisle, Pa., was founded in 1879 by Gen. Richard Henry Pratt, a Civil War veteran and former commander of the Buffalo soldiers of the 10th Cavalry. Through his experiences in the far west, Pratt developed a loathing for the Bureau of Indian Affairs, which he regarded as hopelessly inefficient and corrupt, and he was led to develop his own solutions to the "Indian problem." After being appointed commander at Fort Marion in St. Augustine, Fla., guarding over Kiowa, Cheyenne, and Arapaho hostages who refused to live on reservations, he had his first opportunity to act on his theories, which were intended as an alternative to extermination for both pacifying Indians and alleviating their social conditions.
Pratt's thoughts on Indian education drew upon disparate sources. Influenced by Quaker educators, who had eighty years of experience in attempting to instill white values in Indians, Pratt latched onto the idea of using boarding schools as a means of separating Indians from their native cultures and socializing them into "civilized" life, while preparing them for work in industrial and manual labor. Given new white names to replace their Indian ones, the students were prohibited from speaking their native languages, were instructed in Christianity, and were fed, clothed, and housed under strict military discipline.
For his first foray into Indian education, Pratt arranged for 17 Kiowa and Cheyenne prisoners at Fort Marion to enroll at the newly founded Hampton Institute, a school dedicated to providing a vocational, industrial education for freed slaves and Indians. At the same time, he lobbied the government to allow him to establish his own vocational school, receiving permission from the Department of the Interior during the summer of 1879 to use the abandoned barracks at Carlisle, Pa., for that purpose. That September, he recruited 82 Lakota students from the Rosebud and Pine Ridge Agencies, including five of Spotted Tail's sons, a daughter, and a granddaughter. Two of his Hampton students recruited other students among the Kiowa and Cheyenne, and on October 6, 1879, the first students of the Carlisle Training School took residence.
Over the course of its 39 years, over 10,000 students were enrolled at the Carlisle School drawn from tribes all across the continent. Until it closed in 1918, Carlisle served as a model for dozens of other boarding schools who adopted the concept of "civilizing the Indian" by stripping away Indian identity.
Mad Wolf, Cheyenne Chief; Man on Cloud, Cheyenne Chief; Pratt, Richard Henry, 1840-1924; Spotted Tail, Brule Sioux Chief, 1823-1881; United States Indian School (Carlisle, Pa.)--Photographs; White Buffalo, Cheyenne Chief; Albumen prints; Boudoir card photographs; Cabinet card photographs; Cheyenne Indians--Photographs; Creek Indians--Photographs; Dakota Indians--Photographs; Ethnographic photography; Indians of North America--Photographs; Laguna Indians--Photographs; Lipan Indians--Photographs; Pueblo Indians--Photographs
- Speck-Choate Photograph Collection, 1879-1881; 0.25 linear feet (Box 1)
  - The first Indian boy who applied to Capt. Pratt -- Ft. Berthold, D. T., Sept. 19, 1878 -- for education at Hampton, Va., was called out of the medicine lodge painted and decorated as seen in the picture, ca.1880; 1a; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Title written on verso.
  - Cheyenne, Walter Matches, ca.1880; 1b; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Ki ot se (Mary Perry), Wat ye eh (Benj. Thomas) Koush te ah (John Menaul). No. 2 Laguna Pueblos, ca.1880; 1c; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Justine La Framboise, Nancy Renville, Cheyenne Lucy, Anne Louisa, ca.1880; 1d; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Spotted Tail, Sioux Chief, ca.1880; 1e; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Miss Hyde and class, ca.1880; 1f; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Ouray and wife Chipeta. Utes, ca.1880; 1g; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Mary Ely, Jennie Hammaker, Taylor Ely, Frank Cushing, Zuni, ca.1880; 1h; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Mattie Reid, Anna Menaul, John Menaul, Mary Perry, Benny Thomas, Lena Carr, Clara Guernsey, Julia Dorris, Harry Marmon, Jose Paisano, Lieut. Gov. of Laguna, ca.1880; 1i; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Cheyennes. Man on Cloud, Mad Wolf, ca.1880; 2a; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Capt. Pratt and Spotted Tail with [Quaker] Ladies from Philada., ca.1880; 2b; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Our boys and girls at the Indian Training School, Carlisle, Pa., 1881; 2c; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
    Title printed on verso.
  - William Peary, Peoria, ca.1880; 2d; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Indian boys at work in saddler shop at Indian Training School, ca.1880; 2e; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Indian boys at work in shoe-makers shop at Carlisle Barracks, ca.1880; 2f; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Sheldon Jackson, John Shields, Harvey Townsend, Pueblos from San Felipe, NM, ca.1880; 2g; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Jack and Kesseta. Lipans, ca.1880; 2h; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Watti (Sheldon Jackson), Keise-te-wa (John Shields), He-re-te (Harvey Townsend), Not San Felippe Pueblos, ca.1880; 2i; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Frank Cushing, Taylor Ealy, Mary Ealy, Jennie Hammaker, Pueblos, ca.1880; 2j; Cabinet card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Indian students' brass band, Indian Training School, ca.1880; 3a; Boudoir card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Sioux boys as they arrived at the Indian Training School, Carlisle Barracks, Oct. 5th, 1879, 3b; Boudoir card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - White Buffalo (Indian youth 18 years old with naturally gray hair). With Indian costume, ca.1880; 3c; Boudoir card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Girls' quarters at the Indian Training School, ca.1880; 3d; Boudoir card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Sioux boys as they arrived at the Indian Training School, Carlisle Barracks, Oct. 5, '79, 1879; 3e; Boudoir card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Indian boys (from 16 different tribes) at the Indian Training School, April 20th 1880. (The ranks on the ground and lower porch show the same Sioux boys who appear in number 1)., 3f; Boudoir card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
    Title printed on verso. Title refers to image number 3b.
  - Group of 10 Creek boys in school uniform, ca.1880; 3g; Boudoir card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)
  - Group of 15 Creek girls in school uniform, ca.1880; 3h; Boudoir card; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902 (Box 1)